Guide to the Stanford University, Asian American Activities Center, Records SC0487
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
1994 Increased Funding for Ethnic Centers In response to events throughout the year, Provost Condelezza Rice approves an increase of 25K in soft funding for each of the four ethnic community centers. The funding was granted on a 2year renewable basis.
1994 Racial Profiling of Asian American youth In an Orange county community where the majority population is white, Asian families protest against a mug book which keeps records of suspected gang members living in the city of Westminster. Over 70% of those profiled were Asian American. Alternative Spring Break The first Asian American focused ASB trips "Asian American Issues: From Identity to Action" and "The Challenge of Identity: The Filipino-American in California" were created to introduce students to the needs of various communities through direct service, experiential learning, discussion, and reflection.
1994 Task Force on Minority Alumni Relations Provost Condoleeza Rice established the Task Force to “develop fundamental recommendations for improving the level of engagement between the University and its alumni of color.” Over two years, the Task Force indexed diversity resources for students and alumni, surveyed minority alumni perspectives, and explored campus issues of potential interest to minority alumni. As a direct result of the Task Force report in 1996 the Alumni Association created the Volunteer Clearinghouse to encourage minority alumni engagement with the University.
1995 Minority Alumni Hall of Fame Established Stanford's ethnic community centers established the Alumni Hall of Fame to recognize the contributions of the University's outstanding alumni of color in an awards ceremony during Reunion Homecoming Weekend.
1996 Proposition 209 This California Civil Rights Initiative ends gender and racial preferences thus ending affirmative action in public institutions. Center for Comparative Studies in Race and Ethnicity Established The Faculty Senate unanimously approves the establishment of the CCSRE department offering majors and minors in race and ethnic studies with a comparative focus.
1996 Listen to the Silence Annual conference open to students throughout the Bay Area and the country that addresses pressing issues in the Asian American community and brings representatives from local community groups to campus to educate participants about these issues.
1996 Queer and Asian group Established Stanford's first student group focused on providing a welcoming and safe space for Stanford students to engage in issues concerning the API and LGBTQ identities.
1996 Funding for Ethnic Centers Renewed Staff of the four ethnic community centers submit the "Report to the Provost on the Special Allocation to the Ethnic Community Centers for Recuitment, Retention, and Cultural Programming". Following the report, the 25K in soft funding is renewed for each center for another cycle.
1997 Anti-Asian Hate Crimes on the rise The National Asian Pacific American Legal Consortium reports 534 suspected and confirmed anti-Asian hate crime incidents, an increase from 458 in the previous year. Anti-Asian Hate Crimes on campus Derogatory racial epithets are found in the A3C in two separate incidents. "Chink" was written in red felt pen on a computer monitor in the couchroom, and mustard was used to write "Fuck you chink" inside the refrigerator.
1997 Asian American Studies Program Established After more than 25 years of student struggle and protest, beginning January 1, 1997, students are now able to major in Asian American Studies. History Prof. Gordon Chang is appointed the first director for the program.
1999 Leading through Education Activism and Diversity Program Established Established as a collaborative effort by the ethnic community centers, the LEAD program provided training for student leaders using the Social Change model for leadership development. Alumni of the program went on to serve as ASSU presidents, national scholars, and student group leaders. The program continued for a decade until eliminated due to budget cuts in 2010.
1999 Spy Allegations: the Dr. Wen Ho Lee case A researcher of Los Alamos National Laboratory is accused of being a spy and responsible for the leaks concerning W88 weapons systems. Racist Email Sent Across Campus An email purported to come from a Stanford graduate student of Asian decent was sent to over 25,000 accounts that included offensive hate speech. Asian American student leaders, faculty, and staff denounce the message and students, in coalition with other ethnic community groups, advocate for a policy against hate crimes on campus.
2000 Cultural Awareness Associates Students participating in the LEAD project called for the creation of Cultural Awareness Associates in the residences to promote cross cultural dialogue and awareness for all Stanford students. The first four CAA positions began 2002.
2000 Concerned Students for Community Centers Students gather to fom the Concerned Students for Community Centers and submitted a proposal to newly appointed University Provost John Etchemendy requesting increased funding, space and maintenance for the centers.
2001 Stabilizing Funding for Ethnic Centers President John Hennesy approved an additional 15K in soft funding for the community centers. In later years he would approve a conversion of the initial 25K to hard funding and added an additional 25K to each center's budget.
2001 9/11 Attacks & Aftermath Following the terrorist attacks on the WTC and the Pentagon, Arab Americans and South Asians encounter hostile discrimination and are victims of hate crimes. Hate Crimes in the Quad Hate crime written in classrooms during Winter Quarter finals. They read: "Rape all Asian b*** and dump them," "F** Sp**!", "White man is King!", "Nuke Arabs", "N***s don't get it, this is a White only class." Police and Stanford administrators cover up graffiti and did not disclose the threatening contents until the Stanford Daily and San Francisco Chronicle broke the story.
2002 Abercrombie & Fitch Campaign Stanford students launch a nation-wide boycott of Abercrombie and Fitch to protest T-shirts with stereotypical caricatures of Asians Americans, resulting in the shirts being pulled from stores.
2002-2004 Increasing Diversity in Student Organizations New student organizations emerge representing not only increased ethnic diversity but also socio-political diversity in the community. New groups include the Stanford Asian American Activism Committee, the Multiracial Identified Community at Stanford, Malaysians at Stanford, Pakistanis at Stanford, Muslim Student Awareness Network, Bhangra,Hindi Film Dance, Noopor, Kayumanggi, and the sorority Sigma Psi Zeta as well as many others.
2003 Books Not Bombs Students march, rally, and conduct a teach-in calling for Books Not Bombs at the Quad to protest impending US military action in Iraq.
2003-2004 Focus on Filipino, Vietnamese & South Asian Students The Asian American Activities Center launches new Speaker Series focused on smaller Filipino, Vietnamese and South Asian communities.
2004 Asian American Activities Center New Associate Dean & Director, Cindy Ng After serving as the Assistant Director for 13 years, Cindy Ng was promoted to Associate Dean of Students and Director of the Asian American Activities Center after former Director Rick Yuen transitioned to the Office of Judicial Affairs. Shelley Tadaki '00, MA'03 was hired as the new Associate Director
2004 Task Force on Minority Alumni Relations Report In recognition of the increasingly diverse alumni community and the growing diversity of the student body, the Board of Trustees convened a second Task Force on Minority Alumni Relations in 2001. The group researched alumni perceptions and concerns and released a report in 2004 encouraging University leadership to: increase minority alumni participation in leadership roles throught the University; cultivate minority alumni as donors; and increase faculty diversity. Stanford's first ever Minority Alumni Conference was held at the time the report was released. | "Filipino Leaders Eye on the Future", South Asian Women Leaders in Focus, and Vietnamese Leaders Series
2004 Refugee Resettlement The most recent wave of Hmong refugees arrives from Wat Tham Krabok in Thailand after the closure of the last refugee camps. Advancing Diversity in Asian American Admissions Over forty students stage a protest at Dean of Admissions Robin Mamlet’s office to demand an increase in Filipino and Southeast Asian American student outreach and admissions acceptances.
2004 Anti-Hmong Sentiment Builds Hmong hunter, Chai Vang, is charged with six counts of murder and two counts of attempted murder after being caught trespassing and returning fire. Racial slurs against Hmong proliferate in the mid-east in response. Vang is found guilty of all counts and sentenced to 6 life sentences.
2005 Hurricane Katrina Hurricane Katrina hits the US Gulf Coast. Approximately 400,000 residents were displaced including many Vietnamese Americans who faced property loss, elimination of their fishing businesses, and for some, a return of PTSD symptoms triggered by similarites to their refugee experience in coming to the US. 9066/911: Community & Identity in Wartime America The Asian American Activities Center marks the 5th Anniversary of 9/11 with a panel titled, From 9066 to 9/11, featuring leaders of the Muslm community, Japanese American community, and Civil Rights leaders who discussed parallels between anti-Japanese hysteria during WW II and anti Muslim, Sikh hysteria post 9/11.
2006 Chinese Alumni Club Commemoration George Leong '47 and fellow Chinese Clubhouse alumni raise funds to support the Asian American Acticities Center which carries on the sense of place that was so important to them as students in the 1940s. Funds go to furnish the Old Union Clubhouse Ballroom and a plaque is installed recognizing the contributions of the Chinese alumni.
2006 First Generation Experience for Stanford Students Recognizing unique challenges faced by first generation college students, the Asian American Activities Center takes the lead in hosting the first student panel during admit weekend focused on the "First Generation Student Experience at Stanford".
2006 Asian American Student Health & Well Being Study The Asian American Activities Center convened a Task Force to examine mental health concerns for Asian American students after several suicides. The following year, a first of it's kind survey was sent out to all self-identified Asian American students gathering information on health & well being as well as help seeking behavior. Findings led to the establishment of the After Dark Program at the Asian American Activities Center focusing on mental health concerns.
2006 Okada House Targeted with Racial Slurs After imposter student Azia Kim was discovered, Okada house residents are targets of anti-asian attacks and racist reactions including fraternities shouting "F---Okada" and "Azia Kim" in mock Asian accents; Asian American female residents were harassed as if they were Azia Ki; a member of a fraternitiy urinated on the dorm front lawn as others yelled "F---Okada". Resident staff and student leaders of the Asian American community stood up for themselves and filed an Acts of Intolerance complaint resulting in disciplinary action. Also, the following year an ill-humored ASSU t-shirt mocking the mental health of Azia Kim was pulled after Asian American student leaders protested the use of student fees forsuch a design.
2007 Sweat Free Stanford Students from the Stanford Asian American Activism Committee launch a campaign urging the University to join the Worker Rights Consortium and adopt a manufacturing Code of Conduct guaranteeing workers of factories producing Stanford apparel basic human rights. In May, students sit-in at the President's Office and 11 students are arrested. The protest resulted in Stanford joining the WRC.
2007 Anti-Hmong Violence Cha Vang is killed in a hunting accident. An all white jury charges his killer, James Nichols with second degree intentional homicide rather than the original first degree murder. Questions of whether this was a retaliation killing for Chai Vang's case a few years earlier arise. Homg Student Union and Stanford Khmer Association Established As a result of the student push for increased outreach to the Southeast Asian community, the first Hmong and Khmer student groups are formed on campus providing support for these smaller communities.
2008 Statewide Hmong Issues Conference at Stanford Students from the Hmong Student Union host the first Statewide Hmong Issues Conference to be held at Stanford, drawing an auidence of over 200 from all areas of the State to campus to explore history, culture and issues facing the Hmong community.
2009 Historical Reunions for API Student Groups The Asian American Students Association celebrates it's 40th Anniversary; The Asian American Theater Project celebrates it's 30th Anniverary; and the Pilipino American Student Union celebrates it's 20th Anniversary.
2009 Concerned Students for Community Centers Students gather to revive the Concerned Students for the Community Centers to hold meetings and rallies to protest planned cuts to staffing and funding of centers.
2009 Cuts to the Community Centers Programs & Staffing Vice Provost for Student Affairs Greg Boardman announced $3M in cuts to the Student Affairs division as part of the two year planned $100M cut to the University Budget. Boardman cited "health and wellbeing, academic success or achievement, risk management and compliance mandates" as priority areas in deciding on cuts and all community centers suffered cuts in program funds to varying degress. In 2010, professional staff of all centers were reduced from FTE to 10-2 with half time status & benefits for two months of the summer. One month was restored in 2011, bringing the staff to an 11-1 schedule.
2011 Racist UCLA Girl Alexandra Wallace, a junior political science major at UCLA posts a Youtube video entitled "Asians in the Library" the same day the earthquake and tsunami hit in Japan. In the video, Wallace imitates "the hordes of Asian people" at UCLA and mocked them for talking on the phone in the library with phrases like "Ohhhh! Ching chong ling long ting tong!". UCLA's Asian Pacific Coalition called for the University to discipline Wallace for using "hate speech" and violating the student code of conduct and after the University announced that it will not take action against Wallace for the video, she announces publicly that she will no longer attend UCLA in an apology letter.
2012 Research Project on Chinese Railroad Workers Two Stanford faculty, Gordon Chang and Shelley Fishkin, launch a multi-year transnational research project involving an international team of academics to document and explore the experience of Chinese railroad workers in America.
2012 Asian American Activities Center Staff Changes After a year long national search, Jerald Adamos was hired as the third Associate Director of the Asian American Activities Center following the departure of former Associate Director Shelley Tadaki.
2012 Pew Report: The Rise of Asian Americans The Pew Research Center publishes the findings of a study on Asian Americans entitled “The Rise of Asian Americans,” that gives attention to an often misunderstood racial group, but ignores the tremendous social and economic diversity within Asian American communities. The report notes that "Asian Americans are the most educated" and "has the highest median household income" but does not disaggregate data by different ethnic groups as captured from the U.S. Census Bureau. The report perpetuates the misunderstandings of API's that policy makers still can not fully address in regards to the educational, economic, and social service needs of America’s fastest growing racial group.
2012 Gordon Chang & David Palumbo-Liu named to Endowed Chairs Professors Gordon Chang is named the Oliver H. Palmer Professor in Humanities and David Palumbo-Liu is named the Louise Hewlett Nixon Professor.
2013 Stereotyped remarks regarding Vietnamese, Cambodian, & Laotian culture Visiting Professor Joel Brinkley writes an op-ed article in the Chicago Tribune recapping his experience in Vietnam stating the country is "gruesome" and "aggressive" with a backwards diet of endangerded animals. As many challenge his article, he responds stating "After all half of Laotian children grow up stunted, even today. In Cambodia the rate is 40 percent. That means they grow up short and not so smart". Students from the Stanford Vietnamese Student Association write a letter to administrators with the support of over 15 student organizations to have him reviewed.
2013 Chair of Faculty Senate David Palumbo-Liu, the Louise Hewlett Nixon Professor is elected as the chair of Stanford's 46th Faculty Senate, making him the second person of color in the institutions's history to hold this position.
Scope and Content Note:
The collection includes materials pertaining to the history and recent activities of the Stanford Asian American community, including the Asian American Activities Center and the student organizations affiliated with the Center. Materials pertaining to the following organizations are included in the collection: Asian American Students Association, Asian American Big Sib Little Sib, Okada Teahouse, Stanford Workshops on Political and Social Issues (SWOPSI), Rainbow Coalition, Stanford Hong Kong Students Association, Chinese Folk Dance, Asian American Christian Fellowship, Stanford Vietnamese Students Association, Aisan Law Students Association, Asian American Medical Students, Korean American Students Association, Korean Students Association, East Coast Asian Student Union, Asian American Premeds, Asian Pacific Student Union, Stanford Hawaii Club, Asian American Women's Group, Stanford Asian Women, Stanford Asian Pacific American Alumni Club, Asian Pacific Americans in Higher Education, Lambda Phi Epsilon, Asian American Alternative Spring Break, Asian Staff Forum, Concerned Students for Asian American Studies, Asian American New Student Orientation.
Additional materials pertain to student issues and activities; Asian American mental health; Asian Americans in the media, arts and theater; curriculum for student initiated classes; campus issues; Asian American history, politics, identity and issues; the Asian American theme dorm, Junipero, which was renamed Okada House; Western Civilization debate; Rainbow Agenda; Lewis Jackson case; History of Asian American Students Association; Peoples Platform; Ethnic Studies; Akhil Gupta tenure case; Proposition 187; Bakke case; Asian American Studies; Admissions; Japanese American Reunion; 1994 Hunger Strike; Redress and Reparations Committee and Hearings; Establishment of the Asian American Activities Center; Asian American Theater Project scripts.
Materials pertaining to major events include Asian Pacific Islander Heritage Month, Asian American Art Series, Asian Images, Lunar New Year, Tule Lake Pilgrimage, Korean American Students CONference (KASCON), Listen to the Silence Conference, Extravaganza.
The collection contains extensive newsclippings, flyers, articles, newsletters, memoranda, photos and other records pertaining to: the Asian American Students Association; the 1989 student take over of the President's Office by the Agenda for Action Coalition; student efforts to establish Asian American Studies at Stanford; and, the 1993 Japanese American Reunion. There are also Asian Staff Forum newsletters, memoranda, and email records from 1986-1996. Also included are original minutes and photos of the Chinese Students Club, renamed the Chinese Students Clubhouse, from 1916-1964. The collection contains student and Center publications dating back to the 1970s, including: Fortnightly, Asian American Women's Journal, New Winds, Winds, Asian American Bulletin, the Sourcebook, CommunicAsians, Junipero Newsletter, Talking Stories, Asian Pacific Islander Magazine, Expressions, Asian Americans at Stanford, 1972-73 and 1975-76, Reflections Korean American Journal, Monolid, Asian American Activities Center brochures.
The files and materials pertaining to the Asian American Activities Center and the various student organizations are not complete.
Arrangement note
Within each series and subseries, records are arranged as received from the Asian American Activities Center. The first accession, transferred to the University Archives in 1995, was arranged in nine series. Subsequent accessions were added as additional series and are identified by accession number.
Asian American students--California.; Asian Americans--Study and teaching.; Stanford University. Asian American Activities Center; Ling, Bianca.; Ngai, Nelson.; Stanford University. Asian American Student Alliance; Stanford University. Asian American Students' Association.; Suh, Richard.; Tran, Linda.
- Asian American Activities Center, Asian American Students Association (AASA) and miscellaneous documents, Series 1
  - Asian American Activities Center
    - Asian American Activities Center (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - OSA Intern [Fall 1982] (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - OSA Intern [Winter 1983]; Asian-American Activities (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Activities Center [1983] (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Intern Selection [1981] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Asian American Students Association
    - AASA Info Sheet (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - AASA Account (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - AASA [Winter 1983] (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Asian Pacific Islander Heritage Week (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Asian Heritage Week Finances, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Asian Heritage Week [1983] (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Cultural Night - Asian Heritage Week [1983] (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Asian American New Student Orientation Committee (AANSOC), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Asian American Graduate Student Survey, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Big Sib Little Sib (Asian American Sibling Program) [1983-84] (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - People's Tea House, 1982-83 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Conference on Asian American Community [Spring 1972] (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Stanford Workshops on Political and Social Issues (SWOPSI), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Winter Quarter Activities (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Community Events, Spring 1983 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - ASSU Constitution (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Funding Guidelines [1982-83]; ASSU Announcements (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Locke, California (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chinatown, San Francisco (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Japanese Americans (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Yoshimura, Wendy (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Film Information (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - JCPA (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Indochinese Refugees (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - SEC Copies (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - To be completed (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The University of California Student Lobby (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - RF Minutes -- WB (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Little Tokyo Peoples Rights Organization (LTPRO) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Media and Publicity (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Iran (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Women (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - A C Keys (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Levasseur, Patricia; Identity Patterns among Filipino American Youth (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - AAPLA, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Asian American Students' Association (AASA) records, Series 2
  - AASA: News and Events [1988-1989] (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Asian American Students' Association (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - AASA Spring Dance [1978] (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - AASA [1983-1983] (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - AASA Constitution and Structure Functioning [1985-1986] (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - AASA Flyers [1987-1988] (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - AASA [1988] (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Rainbow Agenda [1987] (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Finances [1983-1984] (Box 2, Folder 9)